Guide to the Irving Hand papers, 1967-1992
Hand, Irving papers, 1967-1992
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Irving Hand papers, 1967-1992
4855
Irving Hand
24 cubic ft.
Correspondence, newletters, reports, publications, speeches, and other documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence and newsletters, principally dealing with the American Planning Association and the American Institute of Planners; also, planning reports, publications, and other documents dealing with planning education and the Institute of State and Regional Affairs, Pennsylvania State University - Capitol Campus, Middletown. Includes articles and speeches by Hugh R. Pomeroy (1947-1957).
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Irving Hand is Professor of State and Regional Affairs and Director of the Institute of State and Regional Affairs, Emeritus, at the Pennsylvania State University, Harrisburg.
CURRICULUM VITAE (May 1991)
Aug. 1972 to date Professor of State and Regional Planning and Director, Institute of State and Regional Affairs, The Pennsylvania State University -- Capitol Campus, Middletown, Pennsylvania 17057
1985 Acting Director, Division of Public Affairs
1953-1964 Planning Director, Nashville, Tennessee, Metropolitan Planning Commission
1950-1953 Planning Director, Tulsa, Oklahoma, Metropolitan Planning Commission
1947-1950 Member of Staff, Westchester County, New York, Department of Planning
1947 Master's Degree in City Planning Massachusetts Institute of Technology
1945 Bachelor of Social Science, City College of New York
1945-1950 Studies in Public Administration, Graduate School of Public Administration, New York University
Course Director, nationally accredited (by American Economic Development Council), Pennsylvania Basic Economic Development Course
Editor, Pennsylvania Economic Development -- a journal published by the Institute of State and Regional Affairs dealing with community and economic development in Pennsylvania
Mar. 1991 Chairman, Legislative/Government Committee, Pennsylvania Environmental Council Task Force on growth Management; principal contributor to policy statement on growth strategies adopted by PEC Board
Feb. 1991 Chairman, Land Use and Growth Management Committee, Pennsylvania Planning Association; principal author of policy statement adopted by PPA Board
1987 to date Member, Chesapeake Bay Agreement Study Group, Committee on Population Growth and Land Development; one of three appointees representing Pennsylvania; produced 1989 report Population Growth and Land Development to Year 2020 to Chesapeake Bay Executive Committee
Dec. 1975-Dec. 1979 Member of Pennsylvania State Planning Board
June 1989 ASPA Award for Excellence: For Outstanding Contributions to Public Administration; by the American Society for Public Administration, Central Pennsylvania Chapter
1986 Award: Professional Planner of the Year; Pensylvania Planning Assoication, a chapter of the American Planning Association
Apr. 1982 Distinguished Alumnus Award, The Graduate School of Public Administration, New York University
June 1974 Honorary Service Award: Council of State Goverrnments/Council of State Planning Agencies
1984-1986 Chairman, National Planning Committee, Intergovernmental Affairs Division, American Planning Association; Editor of Division Newsletter, 1983 to date
1981-1982 President, American Planning Association
1973-1979 Chairman, Committee on Transportation and Land Development Policy, Transportation Research Board; continued as a member of the Committee through 1987
1975-1985 Member, Board of Directors, Pennsylvania Environmental Council
1985 to date Chairman, City of Harrisburg Business Development Executive Council
1978 Member, Special Advisory committee to the Federal-State Land Use Planning Commission of Alaska
1975-1979 Member, State-wide (PA) Advisory Committee to Pennsylvania Power and Light Company on power plant siting
1964-1966 President, American Institute of Planners
Member: American Planning Association; American Institute of Certified Planners; American Society of Public Administration; Task Force on Federal Flood Control Policy, U.S. Bureau of the Budget, 1965-1966; International Federation of Housing and Planning; International Society of City and Regional Planners
Participating contributor, Local Planning Administration, Third Edition, 1959, International City Manager Association, Chicago, Illinois; numerous articles and proceedings, including publications of Transportation Research Board, 1972 Land Use Controls Annual of American Society of Planning Officials, and National Conference on Science and Technology, PA Office of Science and Technology and National Science foundation, June 1972; chapter on State policy and New Community Development in Strategy for New Community Development in U.S., Dowden, Hutchinson and Ross, Publishers, Feb. 1975; report on Transportation Planning, Programming and Budgeting; An Examination of State and Sub-State Regional Relationships, The Pennsylvania State University, Pennsylvania Transportation Center and Institute of State and Regional Affairs, Nov. 1975; Regional Planning: Purpose and Program, a report prepared for the Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1976; Water Quality Management Planning Training Program, a report prepared for the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources, Apr. 1978; Public Participation and the Role of Advisory Groups, two monographs in a Citizen Handbook for Clean Water, prepared for the U.S. Environmental Protection Administration, 1980; Evaluation of District Planning Grant Programs, for Economic Development Administration, U.S. Department of Commerce, 1980; co-editor, The Practice of State and Regional Planning, published by the International City Management Association and the American Planning Association, 1985.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence and newsletters, principally dealing with the American Planning Association and the American Institute of Planners; also, planning reports, publications, and other documents dealing with planning education and the Institute of State and Regional Affairs, Pennsylvania State University - Capitol Campus, Middletown. Includes articles and speeches by Hugh R. Pomeroy (1947-1957).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hand, Irving.; Pomeroy, Hugh R. (Hugh Reynolds), 1899-1961.; American Planning Association.; Pennsylvania State University. Institute of State and Regional Affairs.
Subjects:
Planning--Societies, etc.; Regional planning--Pennsylvania.; City planners.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- American Planning Association, Correspondence, 1983-85 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- APA, Corresp, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- APA, Newsletters, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- APA, Newsletters, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- APA, Newsletters, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- APA, Newsletters, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- APA, Newsletters, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- APA, Telecommunications Task Force, Earl Finkler, 1980-87 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- APA, Office Space Committee, 1982-84 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- APA, President-elect File, ASPO, 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- APA, AICP, Credentials for Professional Planners, 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- APA, Leadership Letter, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- APA, Leadership Letter, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- APA, Leadership Letter, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- APA, Leadership Letter, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- APA, Leadership Letter, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- APA, Leadership Letter, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Insitute of State and Regional Affairs, Pennsylvania State University Capitol Campus, Middletown, PA., 1967-1992 (Box 3)
- AIP, Government Relations and Planning Policy Conference, 1965 (Box 4)
- AIP, 1973, 1974 (Box 4)
- National development policy, 1974 (Box 4)
- AIP Energy policy proposal, 1974 (Box 4)
- UNC Planning Education Symposium, studies of city planning departments, UNC, MIT, Berkeley, 1974 (Box 4)
- Planning Curricula at various colleges (Box 4)
- Zoning Ordinances from various cities (Box 4)
- Zoning Ordinances from various cities (Box 5)
- APA National Planning Conference, 1983, 1984, 1985 (Box 6)
- APA Leadership Letter, 1989, 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993 (Box 6)
- American Planning Association records (APA)
  - Divisions 01-18
    - List of Divisions and Chairs, 1973-1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 01 Metropolitan and Regional Planning
    - Elections and conference papaers, 1972-1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Newsletter, 1974-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Task Force on the Revision of the 1972 Policy Paper, 1974, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 02 Information Systems
    - Misc., 1972-1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 03 Planning Education
    - Misc., 1973-1980 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 04 Urban Design
    - Newsletter and conference papers, 1973-1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 05 Environmental Planning
    - Elections and Membership Rosters, 1973-1982 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Newsletter, 1974-1983 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Conference Proceedings, 1974, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 06 City Planning and Management
    - Newsletter and conference papers, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Newsletter and conference papers, 1976-1982 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - 07 Transportation Planning
    - Aspen Conference on Future Urban Transportation, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Aspen Conference on Future Urban Transportation, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Division activities, 1978-1983 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Newsletter, 1979-1983 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - 08 State Planning [Irving Hand, Chair in 1982]
  - 09 Human Service and Social Planning
    - Newsletter, 1977-1984 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - 10 Planning and Law
    - Conventions and elections, 1977, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Newsletter, 1977-1981 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Newsletter, 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Monograph Series (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - 11 Energy Planning
    - AIP Energy Task Force, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - AIP Energy Task Force, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - AIP Energy Task Force, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Newsletter, "Energy Planning Network" (some missing), 1977-1984 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - National Conference on Energy Resource Management, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - 12 Economic Development
    - Newsletter, 1981, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - 13 Planning and Women
    - Newsletter and Misc., 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - 14 International Planning
    - Newsletter, "Interplan", 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - 15 Rural and Small Town Planning
    - Misc., 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - 16 Historic Preservation
  - 17 Neighborhood Development
  - 18 Planning and the Black Community
- Hugh R. Pomeroy articles and speeches, 1947-57; 3 folders and 2 items (Box 8)
- Westchester Co. material, 3 folders and 2 items (Box 8)
- Hand speeches, 1951, 1957; 1 folder (Box 8)
- ASPO Bd of Directors Handbook (Box 8)
- ASPO material, 1977-78 (Box 8)
- AIP, State Planning Dept. and conferences, 1977-79 (Box 9)
- APA Committees (Box 10)
- Boston Conference (Box 10)
- APA Executive Committee Meeting, Feb. 5, 1981 (Box 10)
- National Eduation Development Committee, Apr. 1981 (Box 10)
- APA board meeting, Apr. 1981 (Box 10)
- APA Development Plan and Budget Committee, 1981, 1982 (Box 10)
- APA board meeting, Denver, Sept. 1981; 2 folders (Box 10)
- APA Executive Committee Meeting, Jan. 1982 (Box 10)
- Stollman (Box 10)
- APA Dallas conference, 11 folders (Box 10)
- Council on Developing Choices for the '80's (Box 10)
- National Planning Policy and lobbying, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
- APA position on the Final Report of the Presidents Commission on Housing, 1982 (Box 11)
- Westchester County, NY material, 1940's-1960's (Box 22)
- APA Newsletters of the Intergovernmental Affairs Division, 1983-1993 (Box 22)
- Westchester County material, 1940's-1960's (Box 23)
- Amer. Institute of Planners membership rosters and publications, 1960's (Box 24)
- Amer. Soc. Of Planning Officals publs, 1960's (Box 24)
- UNPROCESSED MATERIAL (Box 12-21)